This page provides a quick overview of what can be done with Mockrunner when testing Struts applications. The release comes with more detailed examples. They also cover mutithread action testing.

This simple action fulfils the order for some type of product. If there's not enough in the stock, an error is returned.

public class OrderAction extends Action
{
    public ActionForward execute(ActionMapping mapping,
                                 ActionForm form,
                                 HttpServletRequest request,
                                 HttpServletResponse response) 
                                 throws Exception
    {
        OrderForm orderForm = (OrderForm)form;
        String id = orderForm.getId();
        int amount = orderForm.getAmount();
        OrderManager orderManager = 
        	OrderManager.instance(request.getSession().getServletContext());
        if(orderManager.getStock(id) < amount)
        {
            ActionMessages errors = new ActionMessages();
            ActionMessage error = new ActionMessage("not.enough.in.stock", id);
            errors.add(ActionMessages.GLOBAL_MESSAGE, error);
            saveErrors(request, errors);
            return mapping.findForward("failure");
        }
        orderManager.order(id, amount);
        return mapping.findForward("success");
    }
}

				

Now we want to write a test in case of success. Assumed we are working with a mock implementation of the OrderManager, the test may look like this.

public class OrderActionTest extends BasicActionTestCaseAdapter
{
    private MockOrderManager orderManager;
    private OrderForm form;

    protected void setUp() throws Exception
    {
        super.setUp();
        orderManager = new MockOrderManager();
        ServletContext context = getActionMockObjectFactory().
                                                 getMockServletContext();
        context.setAttribute(OrderManager.class.getName(), orderManager);
        form = (OrderForm)createActionForm(OrderForm.class);
        setValidate(true);
    }

    public void testSuccessfulOrder()
    {
        form.setId("testProduct");
        form.setAmount(10);
        orderManager.setStock("testProduct", 20);
        actionPerform(OrderAction.class, form);
        verifyNoActionErrors();
        verifyNoActionMessages();
        verifyForward("success");
    }
}

				

Simply extend your test class from BasicActionTestCaseAdapter or ActionTestCaseAdapter instead of JUnits TestCase. The method names are self-explanatory. If you have your own base class for your tests, there's also a delegator solution. It is used in the next example which tests the error case.

public class OrderActionTest extends MyTestCase
{
    private ActionMockObjectFactory mockFactory;
    private ActionTestModule module;
    private MockOrderManager orderManager;
    private OrderForm form;

    protected void setUp() throws Exception
    {
        super.setUp();
        orderManager = new MockOrderManager();
        mockFactory = new ActionMockObjectFactory();
        module = new ActionTestModule(mockFactory);
        ServletContext context = mockFactory.getMockServletContext();
        context.setAttribute(OrderManager.class.getName(), orderManager);
        form = (OrderForm)module.createActionForm(OrderForm.class);
        module.setValidate(true);
    }

    public void testFailureOrder()
    {
        module.addRequestParameter("id", "testProduct");
        module.addRequestParameter("amount", "10");
        orderManager.setStock("testProduct", 5);
        module.actionPerform(OrderAction.class, form);
        module.verifyNumberActionErrors(1);
        module.verifyActionErrorPresent("not.enough.in.stock");
        module.verifyActionErrorValue("not.enough.in.stock", "testProduct");
        module.verifyNoActionMessages();
        module.verifyForward("failure");
    }
}

				

It's nearly the same but you can extend your test from your base class MyTestCase. You have to create the ActionMockObjectFactory and the ActionTestModule on your own. In this test we added the parameters to the request instead of setting them directly. The framework does the necessary populating. You can use this mechanism just like in the real Struts environment or you can turn it off for special tests.

Of course there are a lot of more methods and features. Just download the release, read the readme.txt and check out the examples.

Mockrunner can be used in conjunction with MockEJB to write tests for EJB based applications. MockEJB usually works with a real database. You can use the JDBC framework of Mockrunner instead of a database. There's an EJBTestModule which utilizes the MockEJB API and provides a few additional methods. You can work without using the EJBTestModule, but it makes life easier, if you use MockEJB in conjunction with Mockrunner.

This page provides a very simple example how to use the Struts test framework and the JDBCTestModule of Mockrunner in conjunction with MockEJB and the EJBTestModule. The release comes with a more complex example.

The following action takes a message parameter from the request and writes it to a database using a session bean called LogSessionBean.

public class LogAction extends Action
{
    public ActionForward execute(ActionMapping mapping,
                                 ActionForm form,
                                 HttpServletRequest request,
                                 HttpServletResponse response) 
                                 throws Exception
    {
        String message = request.getParameter("message");
        InitialContext initialContext = new InitialContext();
        Object home = 
           initialContext.lookup("com/mockrunner/example/LogSession");
        LogSessionHome logHome = 
          (LogSessionHome)PortableRemoteObject.narrow(home, 
                                                      LogSessionHome.class);
        LogSession log = logHome.create();
        log.logMessage(message);
        log.remove();
        return mapping.findForward("success");
    }
}

				

Here's the code of the LogSessionBean. The example only shows the logMessage() method. The complete bean implementation and all the other EJB stuff like the corresponding interfaces and some XDoclet tags for deploying the bean to JBoss are included in the release.

public class LogSessionBean implements SessionBean
{
    private SessionContext sessionContext;
  
    public void logMessage(String message)
    {
        Connection connection = null;
        PreparedStatement statement = null;
        try
        {
            InitialContext context = new InitialContext();
            DataSource dataSource = 
               (DataSource)context.lookup("java:comp/env/jdbc/MySQLDB");
            connection = dataSource.getConnection();
            statement = connection.prepareStatement
                                     ("insert into logtable values(?, ?)");
            statement.setTimestamp(1, 
                                   new Timestamp(System.currentTimeMillis()));
            statement.setString(2, message);
            statement.executeUpdate();
        }
        catch(Exception exc)
        {
            sessionContext.setRollbackOnly();
            throw new EJBException(exc.getMessage());
        }
        finally
        {
            try
            {
                if(null != statement) statement.close();
                if(null != connection) connection.close();
            }
            catch(SQLException sqlExc)
            {
            
            }
        }
    }
}

				

Here's the test for the above example.

public class LogActionTest extends ActionTestCaseAdapter
{
    private JDBCTestModule jdbcModule;
    private EJBTestModule ejbModule;
    
    protected void setUp() throws Exception
    {
        super.setUp();
        jdbcModule = createJDBCTestModule();
        ejbModule = createEJBTestModule();
        ejbModule.setInterfacePackage("com.mockrunner.example.ejb.interfaces");
        ejbModule.deploySessionBean("com/mockrunner/example/LogSession", 
                                    LogSessionBean.class, 
                                    TransactionPolicy.REQUIRED);
        ejbModule.bindToContext("java:comp/env/jdbc/MySQLDB", 
                  getJDBCMockObjectFactory().getMockDataSource());
    }

    public void testLogActionSuccess()
    {
        addRequestParameter("message", "testmessage");
        actionPerform(LogAction.class);
        jdbcModule.verifySQLStatementExecuted("insert into logtable");
        jdbcModule.verifyPreparedStatementParameter("insert into logtable", 
                                                    2, "testmessage");
        ejbModule.verifyNotMarkedForRollback();
        ejbModule.verifyCommitted();
        jdbcModule.verifyAllStatementsClosed();
        jdbcModule.verifyConnectionClosed();
        verifyNoActionErrors();
        verifyForward("success");
    }
}

				

The example uses several test modules in conjunction. The easiest way to do this is to extend ActionTestCaseAdapter instead of BasicActionTestCaseAdapter and to create the other test modules using createJDBCTestModule() and createEJBTestModule().

The EJBTestModule performs the MockEJB setup. It sets the MockContextFactory as default initial context factory and creates a MockUserTransaction. You have to deploy your bean to the mock container. Mockrunner allows you to set the package with the EJB interfaces, so you do not have to provide all the interfaces when deploying the beans. You can also deploy the bean directly to the mock container of MockEJB.

In this example we use the simulated database environment of Mockrunner, so we don't need a real transaction. But we want to keep track if the transaction was committed or rolled back, so we use the MockUserTransaction implementation of Mockrunner.

You can use the MockEJB feature to work with the remote container and you can get a real transaction from the JTA implementation of your application server. You have to call

MockContextFactory.
    setDelegateEnvironment((new InitialContext()).getEnvironment());
				

in the setUp() method before calling super.setUp().

Mockrunner will automatically work with a JTA transaction in this case. Refer to the MockEJB documentation for a detailed description how to setup the remote container.

Please note that you have to use the verify methods of the EJBTestModule when testing the state of the MockUserTransaction, because the MockUserTransaction is a simulated JTA transaction. If the tested code manages the transaction on its own using JDBC, you have to work with the transaction methods of JDBCTestModule. Refer to the JDBC examples.

This page provides a quick overview over the JDBC test framework. There are more examples in the release, especially one that demonstrates how to combine the JDBC test module with the other test modules of Mockrunner.

The JDBC test framework simulates a database but it does not execute any SQL statements. You can use the Mockrunner API to specify the results the database would provide when executing different SQL statements. The framework is meant for testing the Java part of JDBC based applications.

This example class simulates a bank. It can be used to transfer an amount of money from one account to another. It uses a table with the name account. The first column is the account id, the second stores the current balance.

public class Bank
{
    private Connection connection;
    
    public void connect() throws SQLException
    {
        disconnect();
        connection = 
           DriverManager.getConnection("jdbc:mysql://localhost:3306/test");
        connection.setAutoCommit(false);
    }
    
    public void disconnect() throws SQLException
    {
        if(null != connection)
        {
            connection.close();
            connection = null;
        }        
    }
    
    public void transfer(int sourceId, int targetId, int amount) 
                         throws SQLException
    {  
        PreparedStatement preparedStatement = null;
        try
        {
            if(!isValid(sourceId, amount)) return;
            preparedStatement = 
              connection.prepareStatement("update account set " +
                                          "balance=balance+? where id=?");
            preparedStatement.setInt(1, -amount);
            preparedStatement.setInt(2, sourceId);
            preparedStatement.executeUpdate();
            preparedStatement.setInt(1, amount);
            preparedStatement.setInt(2, targetId);
            preparedStatement.executeUpdate();
            connection.commit();
        }
        catch(SQLException exc)
        {
            connection.rollback();
        }
        finally
        {
            if(null != preparedStatement) preparedStatement.close();
        }
    }
    
    private boolean isValid(int sourceId, int amount) throws SQLException
    {
        Statement statement = null;
        ResultSet result = null;
        try
        {
            statement = connection.createStatement();
            result = statement.executeQuery("select balance from account "
                                            + "where id=" + sourceId);
            if(!result.next())
            {
                connection.rollback();
                return false;
            }
            int balance = result.getInt(1);
            if(balance < amount)
            {
                connection.rollback();
                return false;
            }
            return true;
        }
        catch(SQLException exc)
        {
            connection.rollback();
            return false;
        }
        finally
        {
            if(null != result) result.close();
            if(null != statement) statement.close();
        }
    }
}

				

In the first test we simulate the case that the account id does not exist, i.e. the database returns an empty ResultSet. We have to prepare an empty ResultSet and set it as the response for the select statement. Since there's only one select in this example, we can set the corresponding ResultSet as a global one, i.e. it will be returned on every test query. Mockrunner keeps track on every executed SQL statement. When preparing or verifying results you don't have to provide the complete statement string. Usually it's enough to declare just the beginning of the statement string. In this example select balance unambiguously identifies the single select statement of the application. You can also use regular expressions in more complex examples.

public class BankTest extends BasicJDBCTestCaseAdapter
{
    private void prepareEmptyResultSet()
    {
        MockConnection connection = 
            getJDBCMockObjectFactory().getMockConnection();
        StatementResultSetHandler statementHandler = 
            connection.getStatementResultSetHandler();
        MockResultSet result = statementHandler.createResultSet();
        statementHandler.prepareGlobalResultSet(result);
    }
    
    public void testWrongId() throws SQLException
    {
        prepareEmptyResultSet();
        Bank bank = new Bank();
        bank.connect();
        bank.transfer(1, 2, 5000);
        bank.disconnect();
        verifySQLStatementExecuted("select balance");
        verifySQLStatementNotExecuted("update account");
        verifyNotCommitted();
        verifyRolledBack();
        verifyAllResultSetsClosed();
        verifyAllStatementsClosed();
        verifyConnectionClosed();
    }
}

				

In the next test we simulate a valid transaction. We prepare a ResultSet with an amount of 10000, so everything is ok and the transfer can be completed. Simple responses like in this example can be easily specified using the Java API. Large response tables can be specified in text files. Check out the release for an example.

public class BankTest extends BasicJDBCTestCaseAdapter
{
    private void prepareResultSet()
    {
        MockConnection connection = 
            getJDBCMockObjectFactory().getMockConnection();
        StatementResultSetHandler statementHandler = 
            connection.getStatementResultSetHandler();
        MockResultSet result = statementHandler.createResultSet();
        result.addRow(new Integer[] {new Integer(10000)});
        statementHandler.prepareGlobalResultSet(result);
    }
    
    public void testTransferOk() throws SQLException
    {
        prepareResultSet();
        Bank bank = new Bank();
        bank.connect();
        bank.transfer(1, 2, 5000);
        bank.disconnect();
        verifySQLStatementExecuted("select balance");
        verifySQLStatementExecuted("update account");
        verifySQLStatementParameter("update account", 0, 1, new Integer(-5000));
        verifySQLStatementParameter("update account", 0, 2, new Integer(1));
        verifySQLStatementParameter("update account", 1, 1, new Integer(5000));
        verifySQLStatementParameter("update account", 1, 2, new Integer(2));
        verifyCommitted();
        verifyNotRolledBack();
        verifyAllResultSetsClosed();
        verifyAllStatementsClosed();
        verifyConnectionClosed(); 
    }
}

				

Of course there are much more things that can be done. The JDBC test framework is a test module named JDBCTestModule and works like the other test modules in Mockrunner. It provides two adapters called BasicJDBCTestCaseAdapter and JDBCTestCaseAdapter. We used the BasicJDBCTestCaseAdapter in the above example.

Mockrunner contains a simulated JMS environment. It implements all JMS interfaces and can be used to test JMS based code. The JMS test framework is able to send and receive messages and to keep track of everything that happens while delivering the message. Receivers can be plain Java classes or message driven beans.

This page provides a simple example how to use the JMS test module. Although this example does not use EJBs, the EJBTestModule is used because the tested code relies on JNDI. The EJBTestModule utilizes the JNDI implementation of MockEJB. The release contains more detailed examples, especially an example with a session bean as sender and a message driven bean as a receiver.

The following servlet registers a message listener in its init() method. On each request it sends a message with a customer id. The example simulates an online bank where the customer can request a printout of his account data. This is done in an asynchronous manner.

public class PrintMessageServlet extends HttpServlet
{
    public void init() throws ServletException
    {
        try
        {
            InitialContext initialContext = new InitialContext();
            QueueConnectionFactory queueFactory = 
                   (QueueConnectionFactory)initialContext.
                                 lookup("java:ConnectionFactory");
            QueueConnection queueConnection = 
                              queueFactory.createQueueConnection();
            QueueSession queueSession = queueConnection.
                    createQueueSession(false, Session.CLIENT_ACKNOWLEDGE);
            Queue queue = (Queue)initialContext.lookup("queue/testQueue");
            QueueReceiver receiver = queueSession.createReceiver(queue);
            receiver.setMessageListener(new PrintMessageListener());
            queueConnection.start();
        }
        catch(Exception exc)
        {
            exc.printStackTrace();
        }
    }

    public void doPost(HttpServletRequest request, 
                       HttpServletResponse response) 
                       throws ServletException, IOException
    {
        String customerId = request.getParameter("customerId");
        QueueConnection queueConnection = null;
        QueueSession queueSession = null;
        QueueSender queueSender = null;
        try
        {   
            InitialContext initialContext = new InitialContext();
            QueueConnectionFactory queueFactory = 
                  (QueueConnectionFactory)initialContext.
                               lookup("java:ConnectionFactory");
            queueConnection = queueFactory.createQueueConnection();
            queueSession = queueConnection.createQueueSession
                                (false, Session.CLIENT_ACKNOWLEDGE);
            Queue queue = (Queue)initialContext.lookup("queue/testQueue");
            TextMessage message = queueSession.createTextMessage(customerId);
            queueSender = queueSession.createSender(queue);
            queueSender.send(message);
            response.getWriter().
                       write("Print request for " + customerId + 
                             " successfully sent");
        }
        catch(Exception exc)
        {
            response.getWriter().
            write("Error sending print request for " + customerId);
        }
        finally
        {
            try
            {
                if(null != queueSender) queueSender.close();
                if(null != queueSession) queueSession.close();
                if(null != queueConnection) queueConnection.close();
            }
            catch(JMSException exc)
            {
                exc.printStackTrace();
            }
        }
    }
}

				

Here's the code of the PrintMessageListener. The print code is omitted for simplicity.

public class PrintMessageListener implements MessageListener
{
    public void onMessage(Message message)
    {
        if(message instanceof TextMessage)
        {
            //do print
        }
        try
        {
            message.acknowledge();
        }
        catch(JMSException exc)
        {
            exc.printStackTrace();
        }
    }
}

				

Here's the test for the above example.

public class PrintMessageServletTest extends JMSTestCaseAdapter
{
    private EJBTestModule ejbModule;
    private ServletTestModule servletModule;
    private MockQueue queue;
    
    protected void setUp() throws Exception
    {
        super.setUp();
        ejbModule = createEJBTestModule();
        ejbModule.bindToContext("java:ConnectionFactory", 
          getJMSMockObjectFactory().getMockQueueConnectionFactory());
        queue = getDestinationManager().createQueue("testQueue");
        ejbModule.bindToContext("queue/testQueue", queue);
        servletModule = createServletTestModule();
        servletModule.createServlet(PrintMessageServlet.class);
    }

    public void testInitPrintMessageReceiver() throws Exception
    {
        verifyQueueConnectionStarted();
        verifyNumberQueueSessions(1);
        verifyNumberQueueReceivers(0, "testQueue", 1);
        QueueReceiver receiver = getQueueTransmissionManager(0).
                                      getQueueReceiver("testQueue");
        assertTrue(receiver.getMessageListener() instanceof 
                                              PrintMessageListener);
    }
    
    public void testSendAndReceive() throws Exception
    {
        servletModule.addRequestParameter("customerId", "1");
        servletModule.doGet();
        servletModule.addRequestParameter("customerId", "2");
        servletModule.doGet();
        servletModule.addRequestParameter("customerId", "3");
        servletModule.doGet();
        verifyNumberOfReceivedQueueMessages("testQueue", 3);
        verifyAllReceivedQueueMessagesAcknowledged("testQueue");
        verifyReceivedQueueMessageEquals("testQueue", 0, 
                                     new MockTextMessage("1"));
        verifyReceivedQueueMessageEquals("testQueue", 1, 
                                     new MockTextMessage("2"));
        verifyReceivedQueueMessageEquals("testQueue", 2, 
                                     new MockTextMessage("3"));
        QueueSender sender = getQueueTransmissionManager(0).
                                      createQueueSender(queue);
        sender.send(new MockObjectMessage(new Integer(3)));
        verifyNumberOfReceivedQueueMessages("testQueue", 4);
        verifyReceivedQueueMessageAcknowledged("testQueue", 3);
        verifyNumberOfCurrentQueueMessages("testQueue", 0);
    }
    
    public void testServletResponse() throws Exception
    {
        servletModule.setCaseSensitive(false);
        servletModule.addRequestParameter("customerId", "1");
        servletModule.doGet();
        servletModule.verifyOutputContains("successfully");
        servletModule.clearOutput();
        getJMSMockObjectFactory().getMockQueueConnectionFactory().
               setJMSException(new JMSException("TestException"));
        servletModule.doGet();
        servletModule.verifyOutputContains("error");
    }
}

			

The setUp() method creates the servlet and binds the factory and the queue to JNDI. Please note, that the ServletTestModule assures that the servlets init() is called once. In the first test, we simply check that a queue connection is started and the message listener is ready and waiting for incoming messages. In the second test we send a few messages and check that they were all received and acknowledged. We only check the text of the text messages. It is also possible to query the message properties and the message content for all types of JMS messages. The example is not transacted, so we do not check any transaction states. In the third test we simulate a server error. The message cannot be sent and the servlet generates an error output.

A few notes on the JMS implementation:

The JMS test module is not a full blown message server, but it supports all necessary functionality to test JMS code. The implementation breaks the JMS specification in some cases. Messages are immediately forwarded to a proper receiver, if possible. Otherwise they're stored for later examination. There's no real transaction support, i.e. the framework keeps track if a transaction is committed or rolled back, but does not guarantee transaction atomicity. If you send a message in a transaction, it will be forwarded to the receiver, even if you rollback the transaction. The transaction can be a built in JMS transaction or a JTA transaction. Both cases are covered by an example in the release.
The framework never tries to redeliver any messages. It keeps track of everything that happens. You can check that a message was not acknowledged (either by your code or by the mock container) but it does not try to redeliver the unacknowledged message.
Everything executes within a single thread. The JMS implementation is not thread safe at the moment.